What is a web service ?

Integral part of SOA (service oriented architecture)
service = Business functionality to be exported to remote clnts.
server -- service provider
clnt --service accessor

Why -- To export the Business logic (functional logic --banking, customer service, payment gateway ,  stock exchange server BSE , NSE ...) to remote clients over standard set of protocols.

Its equivalent to Java RMI (remote method invocation)
In Java RMI -- java clnt object can directly invoke the remote method (hosted on the remote host) & get n process results. (i.e it gives you location transperency)
BUT Java RMI ---is 100% java solution.
There is no inter operability in that(i.e its a technologoy specific soln)
How to arrive at technology inde soln ?

CORBA --- Common obj request borker architecture
tough to set up. (IDL ---i/f def language)
Better alternative --- web services
Earlier (J2EE 1.4 ) -- JAX-RPC
Java API for XML based remote procedure calls
Today replaced by JAX-WS & JAX RS

JAX WS -- Java API for XML based web services -- Based upon 
Protocol --SOAP -- simple object access protocol (runs over HTTP)
Has additional header & message format .
+ Have to set up Naming service (UDDI --Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration) 
+ Have to set up WSDL (web service def. language)-- xml based web service def lang.

Too much to set up & eats up larger bandwidth !!
So a simple soln is JAX RS -- Java API for RESTful web service
JAX RS --- is a part of J2EE specifications
Known Vendors --Apache , JBoss 
& products --RESTeasy,Apache CXF
BUT it's still difficult to set up.
So spring , being integration master , comes to the rescue.....
-----------------------------
Refer to -- Regarding REST & REST simplified.
-------------
Create restful service project  
Test it with postman
write its clnt as another spring MVC web appliation.



For spring restful web service provider 
jars --spring-web-hib + json jars 

For spring restful web service client --actually only spring web mvc , hibernate validator & json jars are sufficient.

Server side steps

1. Create Spring Web MVC application
2. The layers --service --dao--pojo --DB are the same.
3. In controller layer , replace @Controller by @RestController annotation, at class level.
4. Request Handling methods will respond to different HTTP methods
(get/post/put/delete)

5. For method=get

Can directly return either a resource eg : Person,BankAccount or Customer or still better is can return entire HTTP response encapsulated in ResponseEntity<T>

What is o.s.http.ResponseEntity<T> 
Represents  HTTP  response entity, consisting of status,headers and body.

Constructors
1. public ResponseEntity(T body,HttpStatus statusCode)
Create a new ResponseEntity with the given body and status code, and no headers.
2.public ResponseEntity(T body,MultiValueMap<String,String> headers,                 HttpStatus statusCode)
Create a new ResponseEntity with the given body and status code, and headers.

1. In the controller's get handling method 
1. In @RequestMapping(value = "add uri with template variables")
Return type of the method  = either a resource or resource embedded in the ResponseEntity.

eg:@RequestMapping(value = "/cust/{id}")
	public Customer getCustomer(@PathVariable int id) {
//access id & invoke service layer method
}

2. Use service layer to fetch a resource.
3. Return it to the client.

2. In the controller's post handling method 
1. In @PostMapping(value = "uri")
Add @RequestBody annotated method argument
Return type of the method  = either a resource or resource embedded in the ResponseEntity.
eg :
@RequestMapping(value = "/cust", method = RequestMethod.POST)
	public ResponseEntity<Customer> createCustomer(@RequestBody Customer c) {
    //invoke service layer method
}

3. Use service layer to create a resource.
3. Return it to the client.

---------------------------
Client side API for RESTful client

Starting point --o.s.web.client.RestTemplate
Main class for synchronous(BLOCKING) client-side HTTP access.
It simplifies communication with HTTP servers using  RESTful principles.
It handles HTTP connections.

You have to provide URLs (with possible template variables) and extract results.
The RestTemplate is similar to other Spring templates such as JmsTemplate and JdbcTemplate in that Spring eliminates a lot of boot strap code and thus makes your code much cleaner.  When applications use the RestTemplate they do not need to worry about HTTP connections, that is all encapsulated by the template. They also get a range of APIs from the RestTemplate which correspond to the well know HTTP methods (GET, PUT, POST, DELETE, HEAD, OPTIONS).  These APIs are overloaded to cater for things  like different ways of passing parameters to the actual REST API.



1. For getting a single or multiple resources from the service provider.
use HTTP method = get

get API of org.springframework.web.client.RestTemplate

 public <T> T getForObject(String url,Class<T> responseType,Object... urlVariables)
 throws RestClientException
T --type of the resource(result/POJO/DTO)
 eg :BankAccount a= template.getForObject("http://localhost:7070/day12_rest_server/bank_accts/{ac_id}/{pin}",BankAccount.class,101,"1234");

OR
public ResponseEntity<T> T getForEntity(String url,Class<T> responseType,Object... urlVariables) throws RestClientException
& then use getBody(),getHeaders(), getStatusCode() , to get complete details


Can handle in catch block -- o.s.web.client.HttpClientErrorException
& use getStatusCode() & 
public String getResponseBodyAsString() --to get complete err details

T  --response type expected from REST service.
 eg: template.getForObject,("http://localhost:7070/rest_server/bank/accts/{id}/{pin}",BankAccount.class,101,"1234");

1.5 getForObject can be replaced by getForEntity also , to get entire response consisting of status code, headers + body.

How to avoid hard coding of REST URLs in your code ?

1. Create a property file(map of key & value pairs) under <resources> & add REST URLs. No specific property file name.
eg :
REST_GET_URL=http://host:port/context path/resource/{var1}/{var2}/....
REST_POST_URL=http://host:port/context path/resource

2. Supply location of app properties file in master configuration file (spring-servlet.xml) --add util namespace.
<util:properties id="props" location="classpath:/app.properties"/>

3. In Rest Client , use SpEL(spring expression language) , to inject value of the property in url.
eg : 
@Value("#{props.REST_GET_URL}")
private String getUrl;


eg :
RestTemplate API usage
Customer c=template.getForObject(getrl, Customer.class, em,pass);
			

2. For creating a resource 
use HTTP method = post
post API of RestTemplate

2.1 public <T> T postForObject(String url,Object request,Class<T> responseType,
Object... uriVariables) throws RestClientException

url - the URL
request - the Object to be POSTed, may be null
responseType - the type of the return value
uriVariables - the variables to expand the template
Returns:
the created object

Creates a new resource by POSTing the given object to the URI template, and returns the resource found in the response.

url - the URL
request - the Object to be POSTed, may be null
responseType - the type of the return value
uriVariables - the variables to expand the template
Returns:
the converted object
: 
eg :
Customer c =template.postForObject(uri, c1, Customer.class);
			
3. For Updating a resource
public void put(String url,Object request,Object... urlVariables)
         throws RestClientException

Creates or updates a resource.

4. For deleting a resource
public void delete(String url,Object... urlVariables) throws RestClientException
Deletes the resources at the specified URI.
-----------------------------
Regarding Annotations

@RestController : Spring 4′s new @RestController annotation.
Its a combination of @Controller and @ResponseBody.

@RequestBody : If a method parameter is annotated with @RequestBody, Spring will bind the incoming HTTP request body(for the URL mentioned in @RequestMapping for that method) to that parameter. While doing that, Spring will [behind the scenes] use HTTP Message converters to convert the HTTP request body into domain object [deserialize request body to domain object], based on ACCEPT or Content-Type header present in request.

@ResponseBody : If a method is annotated with @ResponseBody, Spring will bind the return value to outgoing HTTP response body. While doing that, Spring will [behind the scenes] use HTTP Message converters to convert the return value to HTTP response body [serialize the object to response body], based on Content-Type present in request HTTP header. As already mentioned, in Spring 4, no need to use this annotation.

org.springframework.http.ResponseEntity<T>class  is a really powerful. It represents the entire HTTP response. Good thing about it is that you can control anything that goes into it. You can specify status code, headers, and body. It comes with several constructors to carry the information you want to send in HTTP Response.

@PathVariable This annotation indicates that a method parameter should be bound to a URI template variable [the one in '{}'].(binding between request handling method parametere & URI template variable)


MediaType : With @RequestMapping annotation, you can additionally, specify the MediaType to be produced or consumed (using produces or consumes attributes) by that particular controller method, to further narrow down the mapping.
